So this is the Chula Vedalla Sutta.
And I've shortened it a bit just to make
it come Yeah, make it concise.
There are many questions in it
and they are asked by a layman called
they are asked by a layman called
Visakha.
And he asks a nun, Dhammadinna.
And the first question he asks is,
"In what sense does the Buddha refer to
the term sakkaya?"
So sakkaya, sakkaya, what is that? What
does that mean?
And the translation for that is Well,
there's many different types, but it's
identity, identity view, personality
view, or embodiment.
So it's
person identified
body. Mhm.
So what In what sense does the Buddha
refer to sakkaya?
And the answer to that is the five
assumed aggregates are referred to as
sakkaya. That is form, feeling,
perception, sankharas,
and consciousness.
So what sense does the Buddha use the
term sakkaya? What What would your
sakkaya? What What would your
translation be for that?
What is it?
Um
personality. Cuz that's it's There's the five assumed
Cuz that's it's There's the five assumed
aggregates. Mhm.
So it's any notion of personality, any
notion of identification with anything.
So that's why as far as the
um extent of identification goes, as
that far as the extent of sakaya goes,
it's to the extent of the five
aggregates. You cannot be identified
with anything else that's not within
five aggregates.
Well, it's interesting to see that the
person asking is not asking what is
myself. Mhm.
What is the self? What is atta? Atta,
what is that? He's asking what is
sakaya. Right. Right. Right. Right. Yeah, well,
Right. Right. Right. Right. Yeah, well,
means he already kind of understood the
difference there. Yeah.
So, what is this person this side?
It's that
ownership. See, you you can't have
See, you you can't have
you can't have attavada. You can't have
the self view without underlying
ownership. But, you can still have the
underlying ownership without a self
view.
So, unquestioned ownership of your five
aggregates is how and why the attavada
exists for people.
It is why they they they they think in
terms of I was in the past, I will be in
the future, and so on.
Now, when you start uprooting that, it's
not going to happen overnight, and it's
not just like a flipping a switch, and
now everything is suddenly not self and
not my atta, and so on.
The coarse
uh
the coarse symptoms of
that ownership that you have in regard
to the aggregates, the coarse symptoms
would fall off. But, you're still going to
fall off. But, you're still going to
have
subtler uh levels of identification and
uh levels of identification and
ownership with what? Well, with form, or
with feeling, or with perception, or
with activities, or with consciousness.
Can't be something other than that.
For him, he's already Well, he already
Yeah. Yeah, he already has has some
understanding. Cuz that question that he asked already
Cuz that question that he asked already
implies knowledge to a degree of
distinguishing between Oh, what is
myself? Oh, right. Cuz see, if he
approached and said, "Okay, that atta
and that anatta that the Lord teaches,
what is that?" Then she says, "Oh, it's
the five aggregates." That would not be
an accurate answer. That would be quite
a misleading answer.
Cuz that is not what atta is.
Atta is the result of that. But what is
that? Well, is that ownership? So,
that's what he was referring to when he
asked about Sakaya.
And yet, can you find any sense of
ownership up up a part outside, away
from this body, this experience as a
whole? No.
So, that's why it it kind of implies
that embodiment of ownership is bound
with this with this form, with this what
you are.
Now, to what extent? It's to the extent
you've been maintaining the ownership
carelessly, but uh
unless a person is an arahant, there's
going to be some degree of it present.
That conceit, identification, and
ownership. It's also interesting that that
It's also interesting that that
corresponds
five aggregates,
it's also the
summary of
the first noble truth of dukkha. Mhm.
It's the exact same.
Not a thing different.
Right, right, right. Yeah. Yeah, well,
it's it's
It's the same insight, really. Just
explain in in different ways. Yeah.
Describe differently, but it's the same.
Cuz the the root the the ownership is
the root of suffering. The
identification is the root of suffering.
The craving is the root of suffering.
So, when there is craving, there is the
ownership. When there's ownership,
there's craving.
But the identification is not explicit,
like I am this or I am that feeling or I
am this body or I Exactly. It's not
It's more um
That's already like
implied in your how you act, basically.
And how you perceive it. I mean, that's
also It it it presupposes. Like any
perception you have, it presupposes
already ownership. It's already already
there as an underlying basis. So,
exactly, it's not from the level of
choice, whereby I choose to not identify
or this aggregate is impermanent and
this is impermanent. You're doing that
with your ownership already.
So non-specific and Yeah, so the only
way to kind of
uh remove the ownership is to to start
undermining it indirectly.
Cuz whatever you directly take to tell
yourself that it's not yours,
well, that experience as a whole is
yours. So, then you That's what we said
like with
uh with uh atta, he would be perceiving
an atta. Oh, this is not self. This is
not that, but perceiving the not self is
done with your sense of self.
So, it's not it's not just so easily
um you can't so easily wiggle out of it.
Yeah, the the second question is what is
the source of sakaya, that identity? And
Buddha answered that. It is the craving
for the perpetuation of being or
existence and delighting and lusting
here and there.
Yeah. That's what keeps keeps your ownership
That's what keeps keeps your ownership
perpetuated, which is what
uh then simultaneously
feeds this gratuitous assumption of I am
and who I am and what I am and to what
extent I am and what is mine and so on.
It's a symptom. It's a symptom.
So, what is the ending of sakaya? Well,
removal of the craving and desire,
restraining desire and lust
till the craving is understood,
abandoned, dispassion experienced, there is no more
dispassion experienced, there is no more
ownership, then thus sakaya cannot
possibly persist.
Yeah, the complete dispassion, abandoning,
the complete dispassion, abandoning,
rejection, freedom, and detachment from
craving. But that's an indirect process in terms
But that's an indirect process in terms
of
allowing craving
to arise without acting out of it.
Is
you're not trying to get rid of the
craving in terms of not allowing it to arise.
in terms of not allowing it to arise.
Yeah, that's a kind of a
topic in itself. Like you you have to
get rid of the craving. You have to
abandon the craving. But what does that
getting rid of mean in
Well, we covered that in other talks. It
does not mean denying it. It does not
mean get rid of this, get rid of this,
cuz that's just another thing you're
doing out of your craving now against
that. So, you're full of aversion
towards satisfying it.
Certainly not it. So, basically, whether
you're satisfying it or you're trying to
deny it or you're ignoring it, all of
those would be acting out of that
craving. So, that's exactly why the
practice of Dhamma is subtle and it's
not just a question of countering when
this arises with that arises. It's about
discerning the middle way in between.
But as far as the answer to the question
as far as the answer to the question
goes, yes, by abandonment of craving.
Now, the next question can be asked,
what how do I abandon that? Well, then
you go to every talk we did on the
gradual training, the entirety of it.
That's how you abandon it.
Um so
that is yeah, how how and it's the Noble
Eightfold Path.
So, that's how you abandon
Oh, well, there you go. You maybe just
read the sutta then.
Yeah, exactly. Cuz there is there is
exactly that tendency of all right. Same
with you, so like, oh, okay, so this is
not myself. So, I'm dealing with it or
okay, so I'm not craving now. I shall
abandon this craving. Oh, craving, get
rid of the craving. I must not crave. I
must not crave. No, that's all just
wishful thinking now and you're trying
to jump at the end at the result of what
Yes, you need to abandon it. Same when
we spoke about the hindrances before
when people can't come to terms with
learning how to be
patient in regard to them, but feeling
fully justified in being averse towards
the mind of
you know, experiencing pleasure or pain
and just trying to get rid of it, just
trying to counter it and antidote it
with a method, with a technique, with
and feeling justified in doing so.
As like, no, no, no, you have to be able
to see that mind for what it is. So, you
have to recognize that well, you are
already within the craving. So, you
can't just I got to get rid of this
craving without that being also part of
that craving.
So, then how do I do with this deal with
this? That's a valid question. Well, you
deal with this by not trying to get rid
of it.
By not thinking it's on the level of
choice or antidoting your unpleasant
experiences that you are fundamentally
still averse to.
But by recognizing, right, that's the
gradual training, the noble eightfold
path, the entirety starting from the
livelihood, uh speech, uh bodily
actions, precepts, sense restraint, all
of that is your way out, not like
something you do on on a side, you know,
sometimes, but then I relax on the
weekends, but then I'm back onto it on
Monday. No, no, no, your whole existence
is being reshaped by that entirety of
the noble eightfold path. That's why
when the Buddha did describe what's the
way out, that's the way out. There is
nothing shorter than that that can be
the way out. If it were, it's not the
way out.
What comes up often is I want something
palpable to do.
So, how to deal with that?
Well, that's too ambiguous. Palpable
stuff. Such as keeping the precepts?
Yeah, that's something I can do. When
you want to look at things that are
rooted in greed, aversion, delusion, you
don't. That's something you can do as
well. Keep your mouth shut when you want to
Keep your mouth shut when you want to
say something. That's something you can
do. Don't go out into the crowd or company.
Don't go out into the crowd or company.
Stay alone in the good. That's something
you can do.
But see,
but it's not what I want to do. So, give
me something palpable to do that I also
want to do and that will result in the
immediate pleasure.
Well, that's not the practice of the
Dharma then.
But yeah, if you depending how you look
at it, there are lots of palpable things
to do and more than enough actually.
Give me something quick. Yeah, well,
that's really what's being asked. Yeah,
yeah, yeah.
Right, but kind of just give me
something that would take me all the way
there without all of this.
You define some something I can hammer
away at. Just straight forward. Just
bump it.
Just give me a view that I can agree
with that will make me feel like I'm
absolved from responsibility and duty
and uh thus I'll be saved. Just That's
it.
So is the assumption
of the You put on the upadana in the in
terms of the five aggregates.
Is the assumption of ownership the exact
same thing as the five assumed
aggregates or is this assumption one
thing and the five assumed aggregates
another? So is my
identity separate
separate
right. from those aggregates?
Or is it the same?
Aggregates um don't depend on craving at
all or clinging at all but but clinging
depends on the aggregates. So it's like
a parasite almost in in
um
What what is a parasite?
Uh the the The assumption. The
assumption of Upadana.
Yeah, yeah.
So upadana is not
the form, feeling, perception,
sankharas, consciousness. is on um But
it depends on them. No,
the the the five aggregates
um don't depend on the upadana. Yeah,
but I'm not That's not the question. The
question is is upadana different from
the five aggregates or not?
Um
No, it's not separate from the five
aggregates. It's not separate. Right. So
if it's not separate, does it mean it's
one of them?
Is it the same as them?
The way I understand it is it's like
um
Well, you you used the word like bri- a
bridging um in terms of it's yeah, it's
like rests on top of the five aggregates
in in
So then it's different thing than five
aggregates. Hm, that's right. It's neither, but
Hm, that's right. It's neither, but
as in it's I was thinking like a simile
would be kind of like rust. As in it's
not uh the rust is not a separate thing
uh the rust is not a separate thing
from the metal,
but it's not
um, it is not the metal in itself. It is
it is not the metal in itself. It is
kind of part of the
it
it's is is not it's not it's neither
the five aggregates, nor is it a
separate thing, the five aggregates.
Right, but can we come up with a better
example then, with a more accurate
example? I see what you're saying, but you could
I see what you're saying, but you could
peel off the rust and you got a separate
thing now.
a separate thing, yeah, yeah, yeah. So,
what cannot be peeled off the five
aggregates, but it's not the five
aggregates, but it cannot be found apart
from them?
Well, we'll put down as that, but can we
find a simile for it?
So, something that's
not the thing, but it cannot exist
without the thing.
The reason why I'm asking for simile
means if you can come up with a simile, you're
if you can come up with a simile, you're
understanding the principle.
Yeah, that's a I'm not asking for a
specific simile. I'm asking for anything
that would represent it. Like a
parasite? Well, parasite, you know, exists on its
Well, parasite, you know, exists on its
own, then it comes and feeds on you.
So, you could separate it from it. You
see, yeah, again, you can kind of
separate it, but
not quite. Like cancer was another
example I thought of that it is
not it can't exist on its own apart from
the body.
Um, and it's not the body, Mhm. but it
and it's not the body, Mhm. but it
Can we come up with with a different
Another one. Something else.
Something else.
That's two already for for me to think.
Something more accurate. I've had one
strike. Something more accurate.
Yeah.
So, it cannot be found
from the five aggregates. Cannot be
found apart from it. But it's not it.
This is So is this Is this thing No, but
I want example. I don't want I'm not
asking for an answer to what I just gave
the answer to.
What's the example? Like any example of
of um
something that is generated by something
else and to that extent it exists.
But if that thing stops generating it,
it cannot exist anymore.
Cannot exist on its own.
Like a fire burning a fuel.
There you go. Exactly.
Candle light, flame, anything generated
by a burning candle wick,
fat, oxygen. Mhm. But it's not it. See, there
oxygen. Mhm. But it's not it. See, there
is a heat in regard to a candle
or light you could say for that matter.
Uh can you just take that apart from the
candle? It's inconceivable. Mhm.
So it cannot exist anywhere apart from
that source of fire, but it's not it. If
you If you touch the flame if you look
at it, you won't find the heat in it.
You won't find the the the light in it.
Um
and yeah, and that's also how I think
other suitors as well talk about it open
on taking up a fuel burning. Mhm.
So the aggregates are the fuel.
No. No.
Well, Depends. I mean, practically
speaking, I don't think you need to set
now the differentiate the layers of
fuel, but you need to recognize that the
assumption, the identity, the ownership
won't be measurable by what you can
observe because what you can observe is the
because what you can observe is the
level of the aggregates.
So
you could say aggregates are the fuel,
but not on their own.
Mhm. What What is it that makes the
aggregates the fuel? What lights them up?
the fuel? What lights them up?
Lust.
Lust. Yeah, exactly. Desire and lust in
regards to the observable, in regard to
the attended, in regard to the direct
experience, desire and lust. That's why
there is a heat
of after there.
That's why there is a sense of self
enduring. That then you end up assuming cuz see
That then you end up assuming cuz see
like all this light here, it's separate
from I I see the candle because of the
light. Thus, the light comes first.
Thus, the light comes first.
Yes, so when one is approaching the
Dhamma, one already finds the fire
burning. Yeah, whether one approaches or not, one
Yeah, whether one approaches or not, one
is already thoroughly Yeah, yeah, that
is that Yeah, so there's no neutral
position. No, it's there's already fuel
and it's already on fire. Yeah. So, you
need to see like if you Okay, so now
this light revealed here reveals a
problem. What do I do with it? How do I
deal with it? Well, you have to find the
source of of the of the fire. Mhm. So,
you can be trying to, you know, dim the
light and then get rid of dissipate the
heat and manage all the all the
secondary, but for as long as the main
source is still being fueled and and and
burning, well,
the fire will carry on.
And that's exactly what the Buddha would
say like, well,
a person reflecting wisely on his own
situation, he will not dwell and invest
effort into questions of Okay, so what
was I in the past? What will I be in the
future? What am I now? How do they do in
this trying to satisfy the already
proliferated craving upon craving upon
craving for answers in who I am and what
I am and seeking safety on that level.
He would recognize, okay, like the
Buddha says, the problem is desire and
passion. Yes, I have all this pressuring
answer I need to clarify, but let me do
things in the order he said you should
do them. So, first keep the precepts,
guard the sense doors well restrained,
and then you'll see that probably 80% of
your questions will subside
cuz they got dissolved now. There is no
more fire fueling the pressure of
finding these random answers.
You realize, oh, that was all rooted in
me just not wanting to deal with the
fire that was unpleasant once some I
became aware of it.
So, you have to recognize what the fuel
is and stop.
How do you stop it? Unto the fire.
By recognizing it. How do you recognize
it? Like you said, by first taking on the
Like you said, by first taking on the
precepts.
Learning the sense doors and then seeing
Seeing what?
How my behavior
affects the mind, so to say. What calms it down
the mind, so to say. What calms it down
and what makes it um
more um wild.
wild.
But what if you don't see the specific
connections? Would you then stop keeping the
Would you then stop keeping the
precepts?
No. Why not? Because basic
Because basic
Because the precepts
Hm, let's see.
Because not keeping the precepts is affirming
not keeping the precepts is affirming
the wrong
view, basically. It's affirming that the
problem is not
in the fuel
but in me being burned. Hm. So, you
already know where the problem is,
basically. Hm. By keeping the precepts.
So, you don't need to keep the precepts
to then find out later on
these connections and stuff that would
then justify. No, you already know.
You already have a sense Everybody does
to some extent. They just don't know the
extent of it. Hm.
But everybody can already recognize that
yeah, I can already If somebody just comes out
I can already If somebody just comes out
of blue and says, "Okay, well, here are
two options. One fuels the fire, one
diminishes. Which one would it be?" Hm.
And then the option the A B C would be
centrality, restraint, ill will, non ill
will, and so on.
Even the most uneducated person, if it's
honest, will already 99% of them will
get the right answer. You already have a
very good inkling what increases the
burning and what decreases it.
Just staying, committing to it,
dealing with it to the extent necessary,
enduring it,
not going back and and forgetting the
bigger picture. That's
where people need encouragement and so
on. Knowing what to emphasize. See, if I
Knowing what to emphasize. See, if I
emphasize to you, "No, no, no, it's it's
when this mind moment of craving happens
when in between that space you stop and
that's it. That's it." And it's like,
"Okay, now I'll get these abstract ideas
that I will confuse for practical
instruction. Everything else becomes
second cuz I emphasized these results of
the successful practice that I don't
really partake in cuz I haven't
fulfilled the gradual training." That's
when people say, "Well, the Buddha
talked about the properties of Nirvana
pretty much being universal what Nirvana
is, yeah?" So then it's like, "Okay, so
then that applies to me as well
because yeah, the five aggregates, they
cannot be appropriated.
At the Upadana is not the aggregates.
There is the element of Nirvana. Oh,
thus I'm already in Nirvana. I don't
need to do anything."
I mean, that's not an uncommon view. The
entire Buddhist schools evolved from it.
"Oh, you're already in Nirvana. Just
stop forgetting it." type of thing.
But it's like you're not.
Yes, in every ill person
in every ill person
there is an element of health. I there
is a possibility of cure.
But it doesn't mean that while he's
still sick, he's cured cuz he could be
cured.
And then it's sticking to it to the
cure, to the prescribed cure, which is
the noble eightfold path.
Then again, as I said, if you're honest,
you realize
you don't need much convincing.
If you're honest, you realize, "Yeah,
you got to sense restraint, of course.
I can't be acting out of these things
and at the same time expecting mind to
go beyond it all when when the slightest
desire or ill will or irritation or
laziness just makes you act and commit
to it and want to not deal with anything
else. That's what the Buddha referred or
one of the the main was it the main
factor that he praised that would like
that he praised that would like
be a common thread from somebody who's a
puthujjana to an arahan would be
diligence. Not perceiving the light and floating in
Not perceiving the light and floating in
the air or having jhanic ecstatic
experiences or whatever else. No,
diligence. Diligently not abandoning
what you know you should be doing.
There you go.
Nothing mystical about it.
Which is exactly why it's not very
popular.
So yes, the desire and lust for the five
assumed aggregates is the assumption
there. That's what
That's why the assumption's there. Yeah.
Yeah. That's what fuels it.
So how does sakkāya come about? How does
identity come about?
come about?
And it's when an uninstructed ordinary
person has not seen the noble ones,
has neither heard them,
and is neither skilled nor trained in
their teaching,
they regard form as self, self as having
form, form in self, self
doesn't know what to emphasize really.
He just yeah, identified with
everything. Uh
Uh
And how does identity view sakkāya not
come about? It's when an instructed
noble disciple has seen the noble ones,
heard their teachings, skilled and
trained in their teachings,
they don't regard form as self, Mhm.
self as having form.
They don't regard feeling. Uh And how do
you not regard the five aggregates?
As uh
yours. Yeah. How do you do that?
So how did that noble disciple
who has met
the wise ones,
how did he arrive to the point of
regarding these things? Did he just
started not regarding things because he
was told the esoteric truth that uninitiated
told the esoteric truth that uninitiated
were not privy to?
So, how did he do it?
By not acting out of
craving This assumption of How do you
start that? How do you start begin that
practice of Well,
virtue sense restraint. Yeah. So, by
hearing what he needs to do first and
actually doing it.
That's the great mystery. That
diligence. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah, he went and visited other teachers
who said, "Well, nobody gets killed.
There's nothing given.
You know, there's nothing lost. There's
no life. There's no death.
There are no brahmas. It's just what you
have. It's just telling him, "Okay."
Then he went to another teacher and he
told him something on the same level or
another teacher taught him how to watch
sensations and so on. And then they came
to the noble one and he told him, "Well,
keep the precepts.
Guard the sense doors. Don't go after
things that are inducive of lust. Don't
act out of aversion. Don't act out of
carelessness. Don't act out of
hindrances. Yeah, of course. Endure
that. The confinement that builds up
again, you have to get used to it. Stop
you have to get used to it. Stop
resisting it. Stop being averse towards
that. Dwell in solitude.
Dwell in solitude.
Watch your intentions.
And uh everything else then
will fall into place. Then the form will
not be regarded as yours. The feeling
will not be regarded as yours even if
you wanted to.
Cuz you thoroughly endured the
unonability of it, which is the was the
scarier unpleasant part.
So, by being instructed rightly,
he applied the effort of sense
restraint, guarding of the sense doors,
enduring the confinement, not acting out
of hindrances, not trying to get rid of
them, and so on.
And now he's killed in in not regarding
form as his.
But he was not just, "Oh, this is how
you do it. Okay, thank you." And
everything else we just sweep under the
carpet and you just come straight to the
application of the result of your
supposed it application. Nothing's real.
Yeah, or just dismissing it and so on.
So, is the noble eightfold path
conditioned or unconditioned?
It's conditioned. Mhm.
You don't just
What's the noble eightfold path? Da da
da. Oh, okay. See? I got it. I got it.
that. I I listed I studied the etymology
of every term.
Yeah. Memorized
Memorized
All the permutations, yeah? I memorized
it. Four different cars and that's it. I
understand the noble eightfold path now.
Does that make it understood? No?
Conditioned by what? The This clarity of
of um
Well, firstly
not contradicting what is being said.
Yeah, keeping the precepts. Yeah, acting
So, righteously. That's the first
condition. Yeah.
And Acting rightly. Abstaining from
wrong acts. By body.
By speech.
Then through that it's possible to to
see the danger of acting out of craving.
It's a Yeah, and But see, what will
um
What also?
See See, if you're not acting out of
desire, ill will, hindrances.
Uh if you have heard the Dharma, you're
not acting out of these things. What
else is being developed there? Well,
Well,
What are you developing by not acting?
Strengthening perspective. What is the
strengthening of the mind? It's samadhi.
It's composure.
Mhm. So, by not acting out, you're
developing the samadhi. So, that that
would be another
condition, so to speak. Mhm. Of the
path. Sila, samadhi, panna. Eightfold
path. Yeah. Yeah, then by not taking by
getting composure By get By so By not
acting out
By having the mental strength to not try
to get rid of things as soon as they
arise. You are establishing perspective now.
You are establishing perspective now.
It's like, "Wait, but I don't I don't
need to get rid of this.
That was not the problem."
And that would never occur to you if you
were too busy trying to get rid of it.
And perspective is that
And that's the perspective, yeah. the
realms of wisdom And when that
perspective is just unshakable,
whichever way you turn it, the
perspective remains
correctly established, then you know,
there's not much to do anymore. The mind
is easier and easier at the time and and
uh the Yes, of course, yeah. Same like
with any other wild animal. Mhm. The the
the beginning is the hardest.
This is are the three categories, sila,
samadhi, panna.
virtue, composure, and
perspective Mhm. or wisdom.
Included in the noble eightfold path is
the noble eightfold path included in the
three categories. Which one?
Noble eightfold path is included in the
three categories.
Yeah. What does that mean?
It can be summarized in the way that we
just described. Yeah. So, the three
categories are the more fundamental Mhm.
are the more fundamental Mhm.
three aspects that then you can further
define into eightfold path.
But it's really the three layers of
development.
Which we said. Yeah.
Precepts virtue
covered the the the first layer
Yeah, right samadhi composure right
action, right livelihood
sila Yeah. right effort right uh
mindfulness and right composure
and right composure
Yeah. is
uh samadhi.
And right view, right thought
is a category of wisdom. So, these three
categories, are they linear or
non-linear? Non-linear. Non-linear.
Exactly.
So, you don't you don't do one and then
you don't you don't do one and then
exactly that's what I mean so it's not
like see by by knowing the three categories
see by by knowing the three categories
by knowing that the category of sila so
to speak well see there you go
means the category of of some
perspective has to be there
otherwise you wouldn't stick to it you
wouldn't do it
means a degree of composure has to be there
a degree of composure has to be there
otherwise again you would just be pulled
left and right by any idea you have So
they come together
so you will you can then emphasize one
but by doing so the other two are being
developed through
it's not I do one then I move on to the
next one and forget about the first one
no through developing one you're
developing the two through developing
the two you're developing the third one
doesn't matter
so what is composure what is samadhi
what things are foundations of samadhi
what things are the prerequisites of
samadhi what is the development of
samadhi and you you just answered that
that's uh
elevation of mind is samadhi the four
bases of present mindfulness
the foundations four foundations of
samadhi the four right efforts are prerequisites
the four right efforts are prerequisites
for samadhi the cultivation development
and making much of these very same
things is development of samadhi
four right efforts
foundations of mindfulness
and any elevation of mind
composure yeah is imperturbability yeah
so then you got how many sankhara are
there
says these there are three three these
there are these three sankharas
physical or bodily
or bodily
verbal and mental
kaya sankhara vaci sankhara citta
sankhara What is the bodily determination?
What is the bodily determination?
The kaya sankara.
What determines the body?
Mhm. No, I wouldn't.
No, I wouldn't.
Doesn't determine the body.
What activates the body?
What is the bodily activity?
What is the bod- the bodily The bodily
activity.
Yeah, I mean, the answer is the breath.
But you could also like say the heart or
the functioning brain.
I don't understand the
Activity. Activity requires intention.
Yeah, that's the intention. There is a
degree of intentionality and in the
subtle close natural, yeah. It is,
exactly. So, that's why the breathing is
inseparable from the body.
Yeah, yeah. Cannot be conceived apart
from the body.
It's a bodily activity. But yeah, it
does still imply a certain degree of
intention. Intentionality.
Unlike operation of other organs. And
what about being in a body posture?
What is that?
Well, that depends on all that. Yeah, that's
that depends on all that. Yeah, that's
kind of practically Obviously, you could
practice on the level of bodily
postures, but it's not uh
it's not necessarily always revealing
the activity aspect.
And breathing is.
It is the question.
Body posture is more like on the level
of yeah.
Recognizing there is a beating heart.
But you don't really have that
It doesn't require that direct say or
direct input. You just find yourself
seated or standing and so on. Yes, you
had the intention to change, but now you
are seated. However, breath is always
Breath is always engaging. Breath is
always active in that sense. So, it's a
What were you going to say, sorry? Yeah,
it just occurred to me in relation to
your question. Like, you can do a heart
transplant. So, you can take somebody's
heart out, put it in a box, and it sort
of keeps beating. Yeah. But, you cannot
take the breath out in the same way.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, exactly. Yeah.
Yeah.
Yes, so that's why in and out breathing
is the bodily activity Mhm. of the
fundamental kind.
So, what is the
verbal vacisankara? Uh-huh. The verbal to
vacisankara? Uh-huh. The verbal to
pizza. What is that?
Thinking and pondering.
What is that specifically when it comes
to speaking? It's uh
It's uh
first one, thinks, and then it breaks
into speech. Yeah, yeah, that's how it
happens. What is that thinking?
What is the extent of that thinking and
pondering? I guess that's what I'm
asking.
What is the extent of the vacisankara?
What is the extent of the intentional
activity? Cuz there's the sankhara aspect of it.
Cuz there's the sankhara aspect of it.
But, the assumption to externalize that
thinking and pondering.
Externalize between quotes, that's sort
of the problem.
So, is that assumption? That assumption
to externalize? Yes. So, is that a
description? Is that another thought?
Yes. Well, I would say it's actually more
Well, I would say it's actually more
fundamental than that.
How can How What would that be then?
Yeah, well, yeah, I'm not saying that
it's not also a thought, but it's it's
like you can have all sorts of
particular thoughts about this, that,
and the other. But, but then as a
determination for speech, there would be
something which is a bit
which is still a thought, but it seems
to be more deeply rooted. It It assumes
Deeply rooted into what? Yeah,
Yeah,
in in relation to perhaps more
particular thoughts.
So, it's another thought then? Yeah,
yeah, I'm not denying that it is also
another thought. But, what else is if
it's not
just a thought? Cuz you keep saying it's
not I'm not denying it's also not a
thought. What else is it?
Beside the thought.
Can it be something else?
No, maybe what I try to say is that that
it's that it's held more deeply
than sort of Deep to what?
sort of Deep to what?
What is the surface that you measure the
depth from?
Okay, let me put it the other way
around. Are you saying it's exactly on the same
Are you saying it's exactly on the same
level as every other thought?
I already give you the answer before you
asked me.
We'll arrive at it, but
it is quite useful where you it's quite
useful where you started.
Because that's exactly why people don't
understand the extent of thinking and
pondering. Mhm. Cuz they keep thinking
there's something more to it.
But that more
is only more cuz you assumed it to be
outside of your thinking and pondering.
And exactly, deeper.
But if you start looking at the depth,
you realize well, it can only be a
thought. So, for as long as I don't open my mouth
So, for as long as I don't open my mouth
and utter
voice, air, sounds
I am not speaking. Mhm. Doesn't matter
how much deeply I go into verbal
thinking and pondering. Mhm. Mhm.
So,
you want to stop the vachi sankara, stop
speaking and stop assuming the speech
through your thoughts. That's it.
You don't have to shut your thoughts or
even verbal speaking, you don't have to
shut down
in order to be quiet.
Cuz that's not what a speech is. Mhm.
He says like the vachi sankara, the
activity of breaking into speech, the
necessary activity for it
is
thinking and pondering. Yes. Exactly. On
that verbal kind, but you realize for as
long as you're not breaking into speech,
it's going to be thinking and pondering.
Doesn't matter how you feel in regard to
it and what assumptions float around and
if your mouth is all pressured to say
something, breaking into speech happens in its own
breaking into speech happens in its own
domain.
And this does not enter that domain.
Then what determines the breaking into
speech if it's not that thinking and
pondering? The domain of uh
The domain of uh
verbal possibility of speaking.
The domain of having a mouth that can
utter voices.
But whether it does or not still
involves some sort of intention there.
Well, that's my point. There is no
transition of that intention. It
involves intention to think and ponder
and say something which is not on the
level of speech. Uh-huh.
When it is, it's cuz it came on from its
own domain.
The speech comes from its own domain
because thinking and pondering to speak
is in its own domain. Mhm. There is no
overlap. There is no one goes into the
other and then your voice comes out.
Mhm. That's the self-centered point of view.
That's the self-centered point of view.
Yes.
So, if you understand the extent of the
vitarka vicara Mhm.
correctly, it's almost understanding the
limit correctly.
That's what extent means. Exactly, yeah.
Uh-huh. Uh and not to assume that there
is okay, this is the limit and then my
speech is outside which is another
vitarka vicara.
So, you realize well,
how do then I
access the domain of speech?
Well, by speaking.
That's it. You can't exit it with your
thoughts. In the same sense, your mind
does not sit in your body, does not
access your form. It just overlaps
through assumption and assumes it's in
it and vice versa.
And that's that converging point
of speech, of verbal sankhara.
Mouth is physical, sounds are physical,
tone level of the form,
but it's your thinking and pondering
that does not know its own extent
that you assume.
Like, I have said this. And you will not
know. I'm thinking of saying it. And then the
I'm thinking of saying it. And then the
body is speaking for me.
That's pretty much what I'm saying.
But now you can accept that as
information, sure, but you really need
to see it on the level of your acute
thinking and pondering as a verbal
sankhara.
As a verbal sankhara means that thinking
and pondering determines the possibility
Means talking to yourself in your own
mind. Uh-huh, yes. That's what it means
Uh-huh, yes. That's what it means
practically. Yeah. That's a verbal
sankhara. But it's not speech. But it's not
But it's not speech. But it's not
speech. It's not speech. No.
It determines speech, but it's like in
the Well, see, it it Why why does it
determine speech? Let's Let me stop
answering it. Let me start asking
questions. Why does speaking to yourself
Why does speaking to yourself
in your own mind, why is that a
determination for breaking into speech?
Can you break into speech without having
spoken? No, impossible. That's why. Now, why is
No, impossible. That's why. Now, why is
that why? Well, that's an irrelevant
question. There is no Oh, well, this is how that
There is no Oh, well, this is how that
happens. What is inseparable is that
there is no breath apart from the body.
Just That is the base sankhara.
What is inseparable is there is no
breaking into speech without verbalized
thinking. That is just the necessary basis for it.
That is just the necessary basis for it.
And then consequently for the third
sankhara, the mind and perception and feeling.
the mind and perception and feeling.
It's inseparable from it.
And the reason why I'm saying this is
because speech in particular, obviously,
it's quite relevant for when it comes to
people to to practice meditation and so
on, whatever that meditation means for
them. But the point is
But the point is
no matter
how differently you're going about it,
pretty much what is common is that
everybody overlooks it.
Everybody just wants to shut down the
thoughts and the mental speaking,
confusing it for this is a speech, this
is a chatter.
Well, actually it isn't.
It's It's It's unrestrained thinking and
pondering. Yeah, that's for sure.
But one thing is to restrain it,
harness it,
hone it, and another thing is to try to
get rid of it and get that piece of no
thinking.
Mhm. So, first develop it rightly,
see the distinction, the different
extent, the necessary basis, and then
you'll know how to calm down the rest.
And those are the actual reflections
that even Buddha said to was doing when
we mention in that sutta. Says, "Oh, he
would have a I don't know, a hundreds of
lust arise or thoughts of cruelty."
He wasn't trying to get rid of or stop
thinking it. No, he would start telling
to himself internally,
"This is for my own harm.
Is this for benefit of me or others?
No." Wha- What has this resulted in the past,
Wha- What has this resulted in the past,
engaging with sensuality? Well, resulted
in increasing the the
the the the kind of unpredictability of
my own mind,
the lack of composure,
the bad choices out of non-perspective.
You can tell all those things, not
mechanically, but in relation to an
enduring pressure of lust.
Same, you have pressure of ill will?
Sure. You have a choice to act. Let's
not act for a second.
Stop. Sit down quietly and review it,
as the Buddha would say, in your own
mind. Wait. This state that I'm being
pressured by now.
How many times it happened so far?
By the way, I'm speaking this so you can
hear me, but you should do this in your
own head.
Mhm. Uh how many times I've done this?
Uh how many times I've done this?
I don't know.
Did it ever result in completely freeing
me from anger or
did it ever not make things worse or did
it not ever make me remorseful after?
No. So, it's it's all it's always
universally unwholesome.
That's it. You don't even need to answer
now whether you should act or not.
You would have already subsided that
anger by maintaining the correct
perspective in regard to it.
Now, do that thoroughly day in day out.
do that thoroughly day in day out.
Whenever anything unwholesome comes,
you review it.
Ask yourself direct questions in regard
to the arisen experience, not mechanical
questions. I just go through the motions of these
I just go through the motions of these
mantra repeating mantra questions
to get that experience ahead when I
actually did gain the perspective
rightly. Oh, no, it's the right
perspective, right?
So, you go back to it.
Each time things arise, you question
them rightly verbally, internally.
And then,
yeah, the time will come when you
realize, "Okay, there's nothing
unwholesome pressuring me. Why don't I
stop this
questioning and reviewing and constant
maintenance of these wholesome thoughts?
Let me just
be mindful of this non-speaking mouth
and stop talking even verbally in my
mind." And you would have sufficiently tamed
And you would have sufficiently tamed
your mind by then. And by then, you
could even plan for the second jhana.
Which is exactly what Bodhisatta did.
But by not seeing where the line is,
you'll be trying to get rid of the
thoughts or ignoring the verbal
thinking, thinking, "Oh, that's just
this is where the practice is." While
the actual root of the context and
perspective starts with
verbalizing what is right here present,
not mechanically
like they did in in in Mahasi,
but actually with a question that points
at the perspective of understanding
what's presently endured. And that's
And that's
developing perspective, developing
strength, that's developing samadhi.
That's that the step that kind of
overlooked, because of which you won't
be able to go very far. That's why even
the suttas when somebody wanted like
Maha Moggallana want to understand the
first jhana where the Buddha encouraged
him, he was he told he said to himself
basically first jhana, first jhana, what is first
first jhana, first jhana, what is first
jhana? And started describing the
factors, not on the level of
information, but on the level of
attending what is there and being
simultaneously described
by thinking and pondering.
Without breaking into speech.
But it all comes from this first chariot
of not acting Yeah, yeah, yeah. Well,
see, if you don't put that first
all what I'm saying is you could even
get a glimpse of it. Oh, I can maintain
the perspective. And then
out of
uh lack of the proper development,
you're going to reinfuse it with the
same old attitude of wanting a shortcut.
So, instead of then enduring what's
present, questioning yourself rightly to reveal
questioning yourself rightly to reveal
the motivation in the context, you'll be
just mechanically verbalizing as I said
mantras or like oh, I'm sitting, I'm
sitting, I'm touching, I'm feeling, I'm
feeling, I'm perceiving, I'm perceiving,
completely ignoring your intention
behind it. So, yeah.
Verbalize whatever you want and then
verbalize the question why are you
verbalizing that in the first place? Why
is this relevant to me?
Why am I trying to verbalize these
things so desperately? Oh, cuz I don't
want to suffer. All right, so suffering
is back here and how am I dealing with
it? Well, by verbalizing random methods
Well, by verbalizing random methods
that I made mechanical because I'm
lacking proper development of sense
restraint, gradual training. I have not
endured things rightly on the right
level sufficiently enough. So, I just
can't help it. I just need a fix, a
shortcut. So, then exactly even if you the Buddha
So, then exactly even if you the Buddha
himself is just telling you exactly what
to do, you will make that into a method
of an impersonal kind.
So, just once again, what is the
physical activator,
the verbal activator, and the mental
chitta activator?
Breathing is the physical sankhara.
Thinking and pondering is the verbal
sankhara. Perception and feeling
are the mental sankhara.
How is breathing a physical sankhara?
How thinking and pondering a verbal
sankhara? How perception and feeling a
mental sankhara?
Breathing is physical. It's tied up with
the body.
That is why breathing is a physical
sankhara. Having thoughts
and pondered, reflected, you break into
speech. That's why thoughts and reflection are
That's why thoughts and reflection are
verbal sankhara. Perception and feeling
are mental.
They are tied up with the mind. That's
why perception and feeling are mental
processes activators.
So, how does someone attain the ending
of perception and feeling?
Oh, that's that's good.
The complete cessation of sankharas.
Well, that's the Yeah, that's the the
most refined one. So, if you can attain
that, it means you should have you would
have abandoned
the speech and the breathing for that
matter.
So, Well, by doing everything else we
said. For this point.
For this point.
I found the answer to this one quite
good in relation to many other things as
well. Yeah. Yeah.
She says a monk who is entering such an
attainment does not think I will enter
the cessation of perception and feeling
or I I am entering the cessation of
perception and feeling.
Or I have entered the cessation of
Rather their mind has been previously
developed so as to lead to such a state.
Mhm. Exactly.
So it's the result of developing the
same principle way before that.
But there's there's no
I am. There's no room here for such a
thought. Yeah. No.
Cuz that's a perception.
Oh, this must be perception in the
cessation of perception and feeling.
Yeah. So
So
Yes, which cease first for a monk who
has who is entering the cessation of
perception and feeling? Mhm. Physical,
verbal, or mental activators?
Which one?
Uh
Verbal ceases first.
Then the physical, then the mental.
So then the breathing.
Yeah. Would cease before the mental.
So how does someone emerge from
cessation of perception and feeling?
A monk who is emerging from such an
attainment does not think I will emerge.
I am emerging.
Or I have emerged from cessation.
Perception and feeling. Rather their
mind has been previously developed so as
to lead to such a
state. So which arise first for a monk who is
So which arise first for a monk who is
emerging from the cessation of
perception and feeling?
Physical, verbal, or mental?
And it's just the opposite basically.
Mental arise first, then the physical, then the
arise first, then the physical, then the
verbal.
So when a monk has emerged from the
attainment of the cessation of
perception and feeling, how many kinds
of pressure or contacts do they
experience? They experience three kinds of pressures
They experience three kinds of pressures
or contacts. Mhm.
Emptiness, sunyata.
Signlessness, animitta.
animitta.
And undirected desire, appanihita. It's
like Non-specific. Non-specific
Non-specific. Non-specific
desire, non-specific intention. Mhm.
It's quite a
I can't even
understand it.
Can't even visualize it. Well, it goes
hand-in-hand with signlessness.
Sign is the specificity.
So, the mind is established upon non-
non-specificity of signs.
Then, the only thing that can accompany
is equally non-specific
Mhm. direction, which you wouldn't even
call a desire from the point of view of
desires. They're always bound with a
specific Yeah.
And the emptiness, exactly. It's not the
emptiness. It's the empty of ownership,
the empty of self.
Hollow of lust, aversion, hollow that
that burning core that was existing
before. But it's still
But it's still
a contact. Well, again, so, technically
um
you you can call it a contact, but only
by abandoning the contact that
non-arahant has, Mhm. you can understand
the contact of an arahant. Cuz that's
pretty much an arahant. That's an
arahant there.
Yeah. Maybe the same as your lifetime, I
Maybe the same as your lifetime, I
suppose, but
So, when a monk has emerged from the
attainment of a cessation of perception
and feeling, what does their mind
incline to?
So- solitude, seclusion.
Their mind inclines
Dispassion. Yeah, detachment.
How many feelings are there?
There are three feelings, pleasant,
painful, and neutral.
What are these three feelings?
Anything felt physical or mental as
pleasant and enjoyable.
Anything felt physical or mental
mentally as painful or unpleasant, this
is painful. Anything felt physically or
mentally as neither pleasurable nor painful, this
as neither pleasurable nor painful, this
is neutral feeling.
So, what is pleasant and what is painful
in each of these feelings?
So, pleasant feeling is pleasant when it
remains and painful in its ending.
Painful feeling is painful when it
remains and pleasant in its ending.
Neutral feeling is pleasant when known
and unpleasant when not known.
Yeah, we spoke about it last time,
didn't we? We spoke about it last time,
yeah. Probably.
Yeah. So, what underlying tendencies underlie
So, what underlying tendencies underlie
each of these three feelings?
So, the underlying tendency for lust
underlies pleasant feeling, the
underlying tendency for resistance
underlies painful feeling, the
underlying tendency for ignorance
underlies underlies neutral feeling.
Do these underlying tendencies always
underlie these feelings?
The answer is no, they do not.
So, what should be given up in regard to
each of these three feelings? The
underlying tendency to to lust should be
given up.
When it comes to pleasant feeling, the
underlying tendency to resistance should
be given up. When it comes to painful
feeling, the underlying tendency to
ignorance should be given up. When it
comes to neutral feeling.
Yeah, so then
but it's obviously not as
practically speaking
cuz what is pleasant
what is pleasant
in a pleasant feeling and what is
unpleasant in a pleasant feeling.
You just read that.
Yeah, when it's
change changes, so All right, but you are then
changes, so All right, but you are then
underline underlying tendency
for aversion towards the unpleasant
aspect of the pleasant feeling.
Yeah. So when there is a
So when there is a
a a threat of change to is something
that's held dear and pleasant, you are
averse to that. All that's still that
same pleasant experience now it's the
aversion underlying it.
Or lust when you equally carelessly
accept it, take it for granted, want
more of it.
And that's again, none of that would be
obvious. None of that would become
apparent if somebody
is first and foremost not acting out of
their feelings
including feeling justified in trying to
get rid of this
lustful thought
that is obviously still regarded as
pleasure, but now because of all the
other views, oh that is I must get rid
of this, I must get rid of this. But now
you are just fueling further that
aversion.
So either way
underlying underlying tendencies remain
and are being perpetuated. So
So
you start with a pleasant feeling that's
underlying by lust.
Then oh but lust is a problem, I must be
restrained. Now you are averse to it.
It's a two. Well, Aversion is Exactly.
Now aversion is a problem.
So how do you fuel lust? How do you fuel
aversion? How do you stop fueling lust? How do you
How do you stop fueling lust? How do you
stop fueling aversion? Acting out of it
or not acting out of it.
So, obviously, when you're talking about
the unpleasant aspect of a pleasant
feeling that is underlined underlaid by the um
that is underlined underlaid by the um
aversion, that will be a subtle form
subtle form of action, but it's still an
action. Aversive thoughts.
Aversive thoughts.
Aversive me- methods.
Rooted in aversion, trying to get rid of
it. That's just the aversion.
That's just the aversion.
And that's why you will remain bound to
that which you're still lustful for.
But if you don't fuel the lust,
nor you act out of aversion,
you get to actually see it for what it
is. But it's it's unpleasant now.
But it's it's unpleasant now.
That's why you can't
well, abandon
the underlying tendency of either lust
or aversion by doing something else.
By act, exactly. The only way you can
abandon it is through attending to it
concurrently, as we said.
Concurrently attending to what is there
a necessary basis for either your lust
or your aversion or your actions that
come out of it. Oh, it's a feeling a
reason on its own. Still in use.
Agreeable, but now I perceive a danger
in any form of engagement with it. Why
did I reach for it? To bring it closer
or whether I reach for it to push it
away? Reaching for it, that's why I suffer.
Reaching for it, that's why I suffer.
That's why I get burned. Not because the
thing is there on its own.
But that will not become apparent if you
haven't attended to it rightly. You only saw
attended to it rightly. You only saw
what you got.
If you haven't attended to it
concurrently, presence of that feeling means all these
presence of that feeling means all these
permutations in aversion and lust and
acting and restraining
because this thing is there.
And you get to see through all these
movements and kind of
options and and and in in jumps of the
mind, you actually perceive right
through it what's at the other end of
it, which is an enduring feeling. You
only solve this whole activity that I'm
being overwhelmed and restraining and
acting and justifying Oh, presence of
feeling, right.
So, when that feeling's not present, all
this is redundant. Okay, well, it's
already redundant by seeing that.
And that's how you calm down.
Then in the same way, you cannot free
yourself from the pressure of thinking
and pondering by breaking into speech
because it's a completely separate
domain. Exactly.
And not just that, like when you do
break into speech,
you realize, as I said, the body's
speaking for you.
You're not doing it.
So, that's actually analogous to wanting
to get rid of the pressure of sensuality
by acting out bodily.
In exactly the same way, you cannot free
yourself from the pressure of thinking
and pondering by breaking into speech,
which is why both those domains need to
be understood in order to dwell free
from sensuality and unwholesome states.
And the pressure, yeah. In the first
place, you are pressured
you are pressured
by the domain you assumed can pressure
you. So, you gave it power to pressure you,
So, you gave it power to pressure you,
and it's actually impressing you.
Obviously, there was no first point
manifested before which you didn't give
it power, and then you gave it power.
You already find yourself overpowered by
it
due to your own wrong notions and
assumptions.
So, should these underlying Should those
underlying tendencies be given up
regarding all instances of these
feelings? It is Are there all always these
It is Are there all always these
underlying tendencies to every single
pleasant feeling?
That is No, not in all instances.
Take a monk who is withdrawn from
sensual desires, from sensual pleasures,
desires for sensual pleasures, withdrawn
from unskillful qualities,
enters upon the first jhana, which has
the pleasure and joy born of withdrawal
withdrawal. Thinking and pondering.
Well, thinking and pondering.
With this, they give up lust and the
underlying tendency to aversion.
just to again specify in light of what
we've just been saying.
So, with a quite a degree of activity
with a quite a degree of activity
of thinking and pondering.
It's not thinking and pondering,
but actually without thinking and
pondering, which is what contemporary
notions of jhana would generally seem to
imply. Yes, yes, thinking and pondering,
but then when you look at it, "Oh, it's
no thinking, no pondering, cuz that's
too active."
But no, no, with thinking and pondering,
with verbal sankhara.
Pleasure and joy born of seclusion, born
of safety.
Safety from fully discerning the extent
of the domains that cannot touch you cuz
you're not in them.
Why would you worry about what's
happening in the prison
when you realize you're not in it
anymore?
And you were in it before cuz your
assumption was keeping you in it.
So, that pleasure that is there Isn't it
pleasure? Pleasure and safety, yeah.
Pleasure and safety, yeah.
Can you lust after this? Possible. Cuz
it's the abandonment of that lust.
Yeah. Do you need to get rid of it? No.
Do you need to get rid of it? No.
Would you fear if it changes? No. Cuz
you know that the change will have to be
within the separate domains that you're
safe from now.
Thus, there will be no aversion towards
it either.
And no fear of that change.
yeah. No fear, no aversion.
And then, uh so, what about
a painful feeling? Is there an
underlying tendency to aversion towards
all painful feelings? No.
It says, "Take a monk who thinks, 'Oh,
when will I enter and remain in that
same dimension that the noble ones enter
and remain.
And nursing such a longing for for the
supreme liberation gives rise to
sadness. With this they give up the resistance
With this they give up the resistance
and underlying tendency to the to
resistance does not apply
underneath that.
Meaning they give up the aversion.
Yeah, yeah.
They give up that resistance, they give
up. Mhm.
Aversion towards that painful feeling of
sadness. Yeah.
So it's a
pretty much painful feeling that was
standing for
for
the the domain that the noble ones dwell
in. You just needed to stop resisting it.
You just needed to stop resisting it.
And when he finally stops resisting it,
he's in the domain of the noble ones
that are dwelling peacefully.
Cuz now he's not
Mhm. averse towards it.
So and then
in terms of neutral feeling
is that underlying tendency towards
ignorance. Does it underlie all neutral feeling?
Does it underlie all neutral feeling?
This is now take a monk who abandoning
pleasure and pain
and ending former happiness and sadness
and enters upon the fourth jhana without
pleasure or pain with pure equanimity
and recollection.
With this they give up ignorance and the
underlying tendency to ignorance does
not apply.
Mhm. Under that, yeah.
So these are the last questions.
What is the counterpart of pleasant
feeling? Painful.
Painful.
What's the counterpart of pleasant
feeling?
What is it?
It's painful feeling.
What's the Pali word for counterpart? It
is counterpart, what's it? So I don't
quite understand the
So, what is the counterpart of painful?
What is the opposite? That's what it's
asking. Answer to it.
Answer to it.
Yeah.
So, painful feeling.
What is the counterpart of
painful feeling?
Pleasant. What is the counterpart of neutral
What is the counterpart of neutral
feeling?
feeling? What is the What is the opposite of
What is the What is the opposite of
neutral
feeling? Ignorance. Ignorance.
Ignorance.
I don't know how How that
How that's the answer.
Uh
Yeah. What is the counterpart of neutral
feeling? Ignorance.
Presence of pain pleasant feeling
counterpart would be pain when that
pleasure changes.
Presence of painful feeling counterpart
is pleasant. Cuz it will have to
disappear, the pain. So, then you'll
experience pleasure. The presence is
over. other The other end of it.
other The other end of it.
The other end of it, exactly. That's
what I That's what I was going to say.
The other side of it. The other side of
it, the other So, presence of neutral
feeling it's ignorance. It's ignorance.
No knowledge. Mhm.
The The other side of neutral feeling is
ignorance.
I still don't get that. Simultaneous.
Yeah, cuz you don't start neutral. Mhm.
But in my life to my experience neutral
feeling, it's being not understood. That
is the presence there of that neutral
feeling. Counterpart of it.
Counterpart of it.
Not after, at the same time.
So, So, what is the counterpart of
So, what is the counterpart of
ignorance? Well,
non-ignorance. So, now when ignorance is seen as
So, now when ignorance is seen as
present, well, see you stop ignoring it.
Yeah. That's the other side.
That's the others. It's another
simultaneous thing now.
The That's why you couldn't you could only
That's why you couldn't you could only
answer that question like what is the
counterpart or the other end of
neutral feeling if you had already kind
of
understood the counterpart of ignorance.
Yeah. Yeah. Otherwise that's just all
invisible basically.
To some extent and then
Yeah, you could start sort of
carving it from the inside
but it will take a while.
So what is the counterpart of ignorance
is non-ignorance or knowledge. What is
the counterpart of knowledge?
Yeah. So what is
what is the
um
present end
of present knowledge? What is the other
present counterpart?
counterpart?
I can't think of a better word actually.
So like liberation and more.
Dispassion. Liberation. Freedom. Freedom.
Liberation. Freedom. Freedom.
Yeah.
Presence of knowledge means freedom is
present. Liberation is present. Dispassion is
Liberation is present. Dispassion is
present. So if the knowledge is present
sufficiently long, its counterpart will
be equally present sufficiently long
enough for you to fully then see
liberation freedom as that which is
present now. So what is the counterpart
of that? Of freedom. Yeah.
Well, that's completely gone.
Nirvana. Yeah.
So what is the counterpart?
What is the counterpart of that Nirvana?
That designation does not reach that.
And the non
the non
she she answers Visakha, your question
goes too far.
You couldn't figure out the limits of
questions. For Nirvana is the combination, the
For Nirvana is the combination, the
destination, and the goal of holy life.
Yeah, also Nirvana is the undetermined
so it can't have an opposite. Exactly.
Yeah. So that is the end of it.
Um
This is that
is that
the constant part of knowledge being
freedom to me also points to this this the fact
to me also points to this this the fact
that
the suffering is the ultimate
coming out of suffering is like the
ultimate the
the
broadest intention in terms of So so
what is not what is the ultimate
knowledge? Okay, the ultimate knowledge is
Okay, the ultimate knowledge is
yeah it is freedom from suffering. So so
there's no
intention that anyone can have that
isn't rooted in wanting to come out of
suffering wanting freedom. Yeah, I think
that basically as long as as long as the
just to highlight to repeat the
counterpart it's simultaneous presence.
It should not be understood as or what
comes later.
So it's like as I said painful feeling
is implied
in current pleasure
because current pleasure we have to
change and they will have to be then
felt painfully and that's already
painful knowledge of that the presence
of that pleasure to an ignorant mind
it already implies pain.
Same presence of pain already implies
pleasure because it will have to end one
way or the other.
Neutral feeling implies ignoring.
Now you see ignoring well that implies
non-ignoring.
Not ignoring and
you see
distraction. Yeah, you could say that
and like the eightfold path this isn't
this isn't linear that this is all
it's as we said is the
the three the three
aspects of one development
which is development of dispassion and
freedom from suffering. That's it.